Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
John Davis Hatch papers
- Research Files, 1790-1992, Series 5:; (Box 3-13, 20-21, 24; 12.7 linear feet)
  - Subject Files, 1861-1992, Subseries 2:
    - Archives of American Art, 1990s (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Arensberg, Walter and Louise, 1930s-1940s (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Argentina, 1980s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Armory Show, 1930s, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Artist Equity Association, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Asia, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Baja, Mexico, 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Berg, Phil, 1956-1957 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Berkshires, 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Blue Resist Conference, 1950s (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - "Bone Pile," 1940s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Boscobel Restoration, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Boston, Massachusetts, 1970s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Canadian Artists, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Carrillon School, 1958-1961 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Carson, Marion S., 1950s (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Carter, Morris, 1940-1960 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Chambers, Lenoir, 1950s-1960s (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Charleston Museum Project, 1930s (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Charleston, South Carolina, 1950s (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - China Relief, 1940s (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Christmas, 1980s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Circuit Case Extension Cooperative, 1930s-1940s, (8 folders) (Box 9, Folder 33-40)
    - Collectors of American Art, 1938-1940 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Connecticut Valley Schools Art Exhibition Group, 1940s (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Cosmos Club, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Cuba, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Cumming, Burton, 1940s (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Curtisville, New York, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Copley and West--Death of Earl Chatham, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - de Grasse Memorial Fund, 1960-1990 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Delaware, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Denver, Colorado, circa 1990s (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Denver Art Museum, circa 1930s (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Depository of American Artists, 1930s-1960s (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Dohme Family, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - DuPont, Henry Francis, 1941-1958 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - England, 1960s-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 16-17)
    - Far East Seminar, Berkeley, California, 1930-1932 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Folios, 1937-1941 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - France, 1960s-1970s (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Fulbright Lectureship, 1949-1950 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Fulton, W. Joseph, 1952-1954 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Gar, China, 1930s-1990s (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - Germany, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Glebe House, Woodbury, Connecticut, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 25)
    - Great Drawings, 1960s, (12 folders) (Box 10, Folder 26-37)
    - Grolier Club, New York City, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 38)
    - Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1937-1960 (Box 10, Folder 39)
    - Guthe, Carl E., 1943-1957 (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Harvard Musical Club, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Hayes, Bartlett H., 1941-1961 (Box 10, Folder 42)
    - Hoosac School, New York, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 43)
    - Houston, Texas, 1959-1963 (Box 10, Folder 44)
    - Hudson Valley Limners, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Huntington Library, 1948-1950 (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - I. N. Phelps Stokes Collection, 1920s-1930s (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Iberian Colonial Art, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - India, 1970s (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Index of Design, 1937-1944 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, 1972-1978, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Italy, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Japan, 1950s-1980s (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - J. C. McGuire Collection, 1937 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Kalhein, Professor W. V, 1970s-1980s (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Kribalu Center, Stockbridge, Massachusetts, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Lesley, Everett P., 1940-1959 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Mabee, Carleton, 1940-1947 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Master Drawings, 1980s (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Mace, Norfolk, Virginia (Great Mace), 1950s (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - McElroy Octagon House, 1861 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Mexico, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Miller, Hugh Gordon, 1960s (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Mission House, Stockbridge, Massachusetts, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Museum of Negro HIstory and Art, Chicago, Illinois, 1960s (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Museum of New Mexico, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Museum Reform, 1953-1961 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - National American Studies Faculty, circa 1970s (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Netherlands, 1930s-1990s, (2 folders) (Box 11, Folder 24-25)
    - New Mexico State Museum (The Art Museum of), 1960s (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - New York City, 1980s-1990s (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1950s-1960s, (4 folders) (Box 11, Folder 28-31)
    - Norfolk Museum Silversmiths, 1940s (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Norfolk, Virginia and North Carolina, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Nova Scotia, Canada, 1980s-1990s (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Oakland Museum, 1960s (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Old Curtisville, Stockbridge, Massachusetts, 1960s, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Olivia's Overlook, 1990s (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - OURS Project, 1980s (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Outdoor Sculpture on the Berkshires, 1970s (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - Panoramas, 1940s (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - Paris Exposition, 1906, circa 1900 (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Path of Christopher Columbus Trip, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - Pennsylvania Dutch, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Peru, 1960s-1970s (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Phelps Stokes Fund, Africa Trip, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Phillips, John Marshall, 1940s-1950s (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Phillips Collection, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Price, Frederic Newlin, 1950s (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Print Council of America, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Public Works of Art Project, 1933-1934 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Rhode Island School of Design, 1949 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Robertson, Thomas, 1942-1955 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Rosewell Mansion, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Saint Bede's Episcopal Church, 1990s (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Saint Johnsbury Athenaeum, 1940s-1960s (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - San Simeon, 1960s, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 14-15)
    - Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1980s-1990s (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Scandanavia, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Seattle Art Museum, 1940s-1980s (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Seattle, Washington, 1990s (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Shadowbrook Mansion, 1950s (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Sitka, Alaska, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Sizer, Theodore, 1942-1957 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Sketch Club, XXI, 1973, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Smiths Biographical Index, 1940s (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - South America, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Spain, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - Spellman College, 1960s, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 27-28)
    - Springfield Art Museum, Springfield, Missouri, 1946-1960 (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Southern States, 1990s (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - Stockbridge, Massachusetts, 1985, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 31-32)
    - Stokes Art Fund, 1960s (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Switzerland, 1990s (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - Tall Ships, 1980s (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Travels, 1980s, (9 folders) (Box 12, Folder 36-44)
    - University of California, 1948-1965 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Van Courtlandt Cup, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Virginia Art Index, 1930s (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Waddell, Chauncey, 1965-1971 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Washington, D. C., 1980s-1990s (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - W. R. Hearst Collection, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - West Africa, 1961-1962 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - West African Museums, 1960s (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - WEVC, Norfolk, Virginia, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Index Card Files, 1940s-1980s, (3 folders) (Box 20, Folder 1-3)
    - Index Card Files, 1940s-1980s, (4 folders) (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
    - Index Card Files, 1940s-1980s, (3 folders) (Box 24, Folder 1-3)
- Organization Files, 1930s-1990s, Series 6:; (Box 13-14; 1.0 linear feet)
  Found here are files regarding Hatch's affiliations with numerous organizations, particularly those related to art and scholarship.
  - Abracadabra House Association, 1940s-1980s (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Albany County Historical Society, 1940s-1950s, (3 folders) (Box 13, Folder 11-13)
  - Albany Institute of History and Art, 1940s, (2 folders) (Box 13, Folder 14-15)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1940s-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 13, Folder 16-17)
  - American Association of Museums, 1950s-1970s, (4 folders) (Box 13, Folder 18-21)
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 1930s-1950s (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - American Craftsmen Council, 1960s (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1940s (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Chesterwood (Daniel Chester French's Studio), 1960s-1970s (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - College Art Association, 1951-1961, (2 folders) (Box 13, Folder 26-27)
  - Committee on Conservation of Cultural Resources, 1940s (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Coordinated Art Program, The Atlanta University Center Colleges, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Don Quixote Club, 1990s (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - Early American Industries Association, 1941-1990s, (3 folders) (Box 13, Folder 31-33)
  - Harvard Musical Association, 1970s (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - Indian Culture Information Campaign, 1960s (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Institute of American Studies, 1930s-1970s (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - International Council of Museums, 1947-1959 (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - International Federation of Landscape Architects, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - International Fine Arts Council, 1955-1957 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - International Institute of Iberian Colonial Art, 1970s-1980s (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Master Drawing Association, 1940s-1990s, (4 folders) (Box 14, Folder 1-4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1980s, (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 5-7)
  - Rotary Club, 1980s-1990s, (3 folders) (Box 14, Folder 8-10)
  - Society of Architectural Historials, 1955-1963 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities, 1930s (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Southern Berkshires Community Arts Council, 1970s-1980s, (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
  - Southeastern Museums Conference, 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 15-16)
  - Stokes Historical Commission, 1960s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Sunny Side Acres Historical Society, 1990s (Box 14, Folder 18)
- Teaching and Education Files, 1930s-1993, Series 7:; (Box 14-15; 1.0 linear feet)
  Teaching files relate to Hatch's work as an instructor at the University of Massachusetts and the University of Oregon. Also found are records of Hatch's continuing education courses at St. John's College in New Mexico in the 1990s.
  - General, 1930s (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Lecture Outlines and Scripts, circa 1940s, (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 20-21)
  - Notes, 1930s-1940s (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Reports and Notes, 1930s-1940s (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - St. John's College, 1990-1993, (2 folders) (Box 14, Folder 24-25)
  - St. John's College, 1990-1993, (6 folders) (Box 15, Folder 1-6)
  - University of Massachusetts, 1940s (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - University of Oregon, 1948-1949, (4 folders) (Box 15, Folder 8-11)
- Writings and Notes, 1936-1990s, Series 8:; (Box 15; 0.3 linear feet)
  Writings by Hatch consist primarily of short essays, lists, lecture and class notes, and artists' biographies.
  - "A Study of Travelling Exhibitions," 1936 (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - "Early Painters of the Upper Hudson," 1942 (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - "London for the Great Chinese Exhibition," 1973 (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - "Non Objective Art in Creative Photography," by Leo Katz, circa 1950s (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - "Paintings by Contemporaries," 1949 (Box 15, Folder 27)
  - "The Problem of the Spiked Heel," 1964 (Box 15, Folder 28)
  - "Walls Tell a Story--Furniture of the Region," 1942 (Box 15, Folder 29)
  - "WPA Sales Galleries," 1938 (Box 15, Folder 30)
  - Book Reviews by Hatch, circa 1950s (Box 15, Folder 31)
  - Lecture Notes--Prof. William Sawitzky, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 32)
  - Lecture Notes--Yale University, 1940 (Box 15, Folder 33)
  - Lecture from American Association of Museums, circa 1941 (Box 15, Folder 34)
  - Lists, 1940s-1960s (Box 15, Folder 35)
  - Lists of Art Books, 1949 (Box 15, Folder 36)
  - Notes, General, 1950s-1960s, (4 folders) (Box 15, Folder 37-40)
  - Reports, 1972 (Box 15, Folder 41)
  - Short Artist Biographies, 1959 (Box 15, Folder 42)
  - Writings by Hatch, 1970s-1990s (Box 15, Folder 43)
- Printed Material, 1870s-1990s, Series 9:; (Box 15-19, 22, 25-26, OV1; 5.9 linear feet)
  Printed materials include catalogs from the American Drawing Annual exhibition from the 1940s-1950s, printed articles annotated by Hatch; blank forms, catalogs of works of art owned by Hatch, other exhibition catalogs and announcements, clippings, pricelists, and published works.
  Printed materials are minimally processed according to Hatch's original order and folder titles.
  - Albany Institute Publications, 1940s (Box 15, Folder 44)
  - American Drawing Annual Catalogs, 1940s-1950s, (3 folders) (Box 15, Folder 45-47)
  - Art Related Catalogs and Pamphlets, circa 1850s (Box 15, Folder 48)
  - Articles Annotated by Hatch, circa 1990s (Box 15, Folder 49)
  - Blank Forms, 1870s, 1970s (Box 15, Folder 50)
  - Bulletins, Art Related, 1930s-1940s (Box 15, Folder 51)
  - Catalogs, of Works Owned by Hatch, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 52)
  - Catalogs, Annotated by Hatch, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 53)
  - Catalogs and Announcements, 1930s-1970s, (17 folders) (Box 16, Folder 1-17)
  - Catalogs and Announcements, 1930s-1970s, (27 folders) (Box 17, Folder 1-27)
  - Catalogs and Announcements, 1930s-1970s, (12 folders) (Box 18, Folder 1-12)
  - Catalogs and Announcements, 1930s-1970s, (9 folders) (Box 19, Folder 1-9)
  - Clippings, 1930s-1970s, (4 folders) (Box 19, Folder 10-13)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1960s, (11 folders; See OV1) (Box 19, Folder 14-24)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1960s, (5 folders) (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1960s, (5 folders) (Box 26, Folder 1-5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1940s-1960s, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
  - Newsletters, 1940s-1960s (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Photocopies of Catalogs, circa 1980s (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Pricelists, 1895-1971 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Radio Scripts, 1944 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art--Given to National Gallery by Olivia Hatch, circa 1990 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - The Hasidim, by Ira Moskowitz and Isaac B. Singer, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - The Sun and the Wind and Mr. Todd, by Eleanor Estes and Louis Slobodkin, 1943 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Poster, 1903, (See also Box 19, F14) (Box OV1)
- Photographs, circa 1900-1990s, Series 10:; (Box 22; 0.2 linear feet)
  Photographs include images of Hatch, including those done by Dorothy Frazer in 1985; Hatch with his family and friends; miscellaneous photos of artists, probably purchased by Hatch for research purposes; photos of furniture and works of art, including those pieces in the Hatch collection; and negatives and slides.
  - of Hatch, circa 1984 (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - of Hatch by Dorothy Frazer, 1985 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - of Hatch and Family, 1950s-1990s (Box 22, Folder 12)
  - of Hatch with Family and Friends, 1920s-1980s, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 13-14)
  - of Artists, circa 1900-1960s (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Oregon Furniture, circa 1940s (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - of Works of Art, from the Hatch Collection, 1930s (Box 22, Folder 17)
  - of Works of Art, 1930s-1970s, (5 folders) (Box 22, Folder 18-22)
  - Negatives, Abbey-White, 1970s (Box 22, Folder 23)
  - Slides, 1970s (Box 22, Folder 24)
- Artwork, 1851-1973, Series 11:; (Box 22; 0.3 linear feet)
  Found here are sketches, drawings, and two sketchbooks from the Hatch collection. Artists represented are Kenneth Calahan, Henry Kirke Brown, Ezra Clark, John Cranch, Jasper Francis Crospey, F. O. C. Darley, C. H. Granger, Seymour J. Guy, Edward Lamson Henry, Henry Inman, Lloyd McNeill, and Julian Scott. Also found are unidentified sketches.
  - Kenneth Callahan Sketchbook, 1973 (Box 22, Folder 25)
  - Lloyd McNeill Sketchbook, 1966 (Box 22, Folder 26)
  - Sketch of John Quincey Adams Ward, by Julian Scott, circa 1890 (Box 22, Folder 27)
  - Sketch, by Henry Kirke Brown, circa 1851 (Box 22, Folder 28)
  - Sketch, by Kenneth Callahan, 1949 (Box 22, Folder 29)
  - Watercolor Sketch of the George Rogers Clark Memorial, by Ezra Clark, circa 1930s (Box 22, Folder 30)
  - Three Sheets in the Wind, by John Cranch, 1890 (Box 22, Folder 31)
  - Cave at Sorento, Bay of Naples, by Jasper Francis Crospey, circa 1800s (Box 22, Folder 32)
  - Llamas, by F. O. C. Darley, circa 1800s (Box 22, Folder 33)
  - Dr. Batehelder, by C. H. Granger, 1839 (Box 22, Folder 24)
  - Sketch, by Seymour J. Guy, 1903 (Box 22, Folder 35)
  - Sketch, by George Harvey (?), circa 1890 (Box 22, Folder 36)
  - Flattening, by Edward Lamson Henry, circa 1800s (Box 22, Folder 37)
  - Sketch, by Henry Inman, circa 1800s (Box 22, Folder 38)
  - Sketches, by Unknown, circa 1900-1940s, (2 folders) (Box 22, Folder 39-40)
  - Watercolor Sketch, by Unknown, circa 1900 (Box 22, Folder 41)
  - Negatives of Sketches, by Unknown, circa 1960 (Box 22, Folder 42)